Guide to the W. A. Stumpf Papers, circa 1947-1955
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
W. A. Stumpf papers circa 1947-1955
University Archives, Duke University
Stumpf, Wippert Arnot, 1899-
3.0 Linear Feet approx. 2,000 Items
W. A. Stumpf was Professor of Education at Duke University from 1948 until his retirement in 1968.
The collection contains surveys of high school seniors (circa 1955) from Durham, Guilford and Wake County high schools, in addition to a manuscript draft and mimeographed copies of papers relating to a 1950 civil rights case against Washington County (N.C.) schools. The material ranges in date from circa 1947-1955.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The W. A. Stumpf Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1989.
Biographical Note
Wippert Arnot Stumpf was born in Elgin, Illinois on January 20, 1899. He earned a B. S. in 1922 from the University of Illinois and a M. A. and Ph.D. from the University of Chicago in 1934 and 1941, respectively. He came to Duke in 1948 to teach in the Dept. of Education and was considered an authority on school administration. Stumpf retired from Duke in 1968. He died in 1991.
Collection Overview
The collection includes 3-page survey forms completed by approximately 500 seniors in Durham, Guilford and Wake County high schools, circa 1955. The survey was titled "Plans of High School Seniors," and included questions about their families' economic status and educational background, living conditions, current activities and post-graduation plans. The forms are arranged by county, then school and sex, then numerically by an apparent score or value penciled on the form. Additionally, the collection contains a typed draft manuscript of a work, mimeographed copies of a proposal to offer the Ed.D. at Duke and mimeographed copies of papers relating to Wilmer Wilborne, et al vs. H. P. Taylor, et al, a civil rights suit against Washington County (N.C.) schools which include a copy of "A Report on a Comparison and the Program and Facilities of Instruction in the Negro and White Schools of Durham," by John W. Carr, Jr. (Professor of Education at Duke) and other material on Durham schools, along with a report on Arlington County (V.A.) high schools. The material ranges in date from circa 1947-1955.
Not all of the surveys have a penciled value or score on them. Since the purpose of the value or score is unknown, surveys with values or scores may fall under FERPA rules as protected information. As such, access to those surveys may be prohibited.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Stumpf, Wippert Arnot, 1899-
Carr, John W. (John Winder), 1894-
Duke University. Dept. of Education
Public Schools -- North Carolina -- Durham County
Public Schools -- North Carolina -- Wake County
Public Schools -- North Carolina -- Guilford County
Public Schools -- Virginia -- Arlington County
Civil rights -- North Carolina
Related Material
Photograph Collection
Duke University Archives
Negative Collection
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection
Duke University Archives
News Service Biographical Collection
Duke University Archives
Dept. of Education Records
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Surveys, 1955
  - Survey, Blank form, circa 1955 (Box 1)
  - Survey, Durham Co., Bethesda High school, male and female, circa 1955
  - Survey, Durham Co., Brag[g]town High School, females, circa 1955
  - Survey, Durham Co., Brag[g]town High School, male, circa 1955
  - Survey, Durham Co., Hope Valley High School, circa 1955
  - Survey, Durham Co., Lowe's Grove, male and female, circa 1955
  - Survey, Durham Co., Mangum High School, circa 1955
  - Survey, Durham Co., Oak Grove High School, male and female, circa 1955
  - Survey, Guilford Co., Bessemer High School, circa 1955
  - Survey, Guilford Co., Rankin High School, male and female, circa 1955
  - Survey, Guilford Co., Sumner High School, male and female, circa 1955
  - Survey, Wake Co., Cary High School, female, circa 1955
  - Survey, Wake Co., Cary High School, male, circa 1955
  - Survey, Wake Co., Garner High School, female, circa 1955
  - Survey, Wake Co., Garner High School, male, circa 1955
- Other Material
  - Durham Public Schools Negro Civil Rights Case, 1950 (Box 2)
  - A proposal to offer the degree of Doctor of Education circa 1947
  - "Rough" draft copies of manual
  - Personal copies, first drafts of chapter manuscript